Welcome to the Negotiations Ninja podcast, where we develop and deliver the most engaging
negotiation content and training in the world.
We host negotiation experts, business people, and entrepreneurs, and discuss what works,
what doesn't work, and how we can improve our negotiation skills.
Hello, Negotiations Ninja listeners, you've got Mark here today.
My guest is the amazing Raphael Lapin.
We get into a conversation about what makes for a good mediation.
Here are all the ingredients that you need within the recipe that makes for a great mediation.
And there is a difference between a great mediation and a average mediation.
We get into the weeds on this discussion with this fascinating conversation with Raphael Lapin.
Hello, Raphael, how are you?
Well, thank you, Mark.
And thank you so much for having me back to your podcast.
It's always a pleasure to talk to you and to be stimulated by your insightful questions.
I'm looking forward to our brief interaction this morning.
I am very excited myself and thank you for your grace.
This is take two for the listeners, just so that you know, we've been having some internet
connectivity issues in the office where we record these.
And I had to call Raphael back in a panic, saying, hey, something happened to the audio.
It's not working.
So thankfully, he was gracious enough to be able to reschedule some time with us.
And we're here today to talk all about mediation.
But before we get into the conversation, Raphael, maybe tell the listeners a bit about who you
are and what you do.
Okay.
Well, first of all, about the panic.
I think I have more panic than you because I thought I was expected to remember the last
podcast and have to repeat everything.
And I was really talking off the cuff as a plan to do today as well.
So I was relieved to hear that.
I don't have to necessarily repeat word for word, as we said, the first time round.
But at any rate, I'll just regard that as practice a bit more about what I do.
So Mark, as you're fully aware, I'm a negotiation and dispute resolution specialist.
So really anything negotiation related or dispute resolution related falls under my purview.
And that involves government entities, corporate entities, and individuals who might be in
a lawsuit or whatever, we sort of work with all those.
And anything related to that, so sometimes in a negotiation, we will provide negotiation
advice and support in complex negotiations, and sometimes would be actually asked to represent
or at least be at the table in dispute resolution sometimes as well.
And the best and cheapest way to resolve a dispute is through direct negotiation.
But 95% of those negotiations fail, largely because of usually when there is a dispute
already, there's a lot of emotion packed up in there, particularly if a lawsuit has
already been filed.
There's resentment, there's anger, there's anxiousness, and all those obstructions to
a productive and constructive negotiation.
So 95% of direct negotiations fail.
If direct negotiations fail, and you still want to avoid a lawsuit, there are some
other options.
The other option is to retain a dispute resolution specialist who will, again, provide strategy
for you, direct you, coach you in how to resolve that dispute, and be there for support as
you're trying to get beyond the dispute.
And of course, if that fails, you always have the option of a mediation where the
two parties will together retain the services of a neutral mediator who will help the
parties actually engage in productive and constructive dialogue, and seek creative
joint solutions to conflicting needs.
So those all are related, and of course, dispute resolution and negotiation are closely
related because in any form of dispute resolution, whether it's direct dispute resolution, whether
it's through services of a mediator, you are using negotiation techniques, skills, and
processes.
So you're using the same framework, whether it's dispute or transactional.
So those are the sort of things we're doing all the time and sort of providing our clients
with those sort of services.
Now, sometimes, for example, yesterday, we just got a call from a larger company who
more than not as common a request, but basically building a capacity within their organization
and having a whole department that manages negotiations, basically teaching them how to
train their people and working myself out of a job.
But that's okay as well.
I don't have a problem with that either.
I think because...
You've just got to make sure the price is right for you.
Well, that's right.
And to make sure there is a provision that they can't use our material, outside their
company, obviously.
For me, they're two aspects of the work that I do.
Obviously, for me, it's a living and how I earn my living.
But equally important, probably, for me, is that it's an area of great satisfaction.
And I'm very fortunate in that the work that I do for my living and the work that I do
that I feel is my purpose and make a contribution to society intersects over the areas of negotiation
and dispute resolution.
And that's something I think that is unfortunate in regard to that.
I do love everything that you're doing online, by the way.
And I will say that for the listeners, if you're listening in right now, Rafael writes
a fantastic newsletter slash article that gets released.
I think it's monthly, is it?
Well, that's a good question.
So lately, during COVID, I've kind of tracked a little bit on that, but I'm doing a different
strategy now, which you might find interesting.
So I'm not putting them out as commonly, but the stuff that I am putting out now,
I'm getting published by third parties.
So magazines or newspapers, whatever, sort of publishing those articles, so that takes a
lot longer.
I'm right down the middle of quite a fascinating 2000-word article about the Palestinian-Israeli
conflict that I hope to get published.
One of my articles on what Biden's approach would be with China and Russia was published
in Foreign Affairs.
And then on the Ethiopian Dam, of course, you probably saw, because I was on Al Jazeera
for that, that has published four or five publications across the continent of Africa.
So my thinking about that is anybody can publish their own stuff nowadays, and there's
no discernment as to what's put out there.
And it's really up to the consumer who may be or may not be educated in terms of discernment
to sort of separate the wheat from the chaff.
So my approach and strategy has now been put out stuff that's published by third parties.
If it's good enough for them, then it's good enough for me, and it's good enough to put
out to the public.
So that has been my approach.
But you're absolutely right.
On my website, Mark, there is two or three years, probably a couple of hundred articles
on negotiation-related topics, all very practical, all providing the information you
can use.
I like the depth of research that you go into on these.
Yeah.
And I do try to learn, a lot of my articles do relate to international affairs, because
I see that as a kind of the apex of negotiation, because there's complexity, there's deep needs
and concerns and emotional issues that are there.
So I learn a lot from researching international conflicts and apply a lot of that to much
smaller conflicts, but a lot of that same research I do apply.
So that's true.
Before we get into the weeds on mediation, I'd love for you to delineate the differences
between arbitration and mediation, because I think a lot of people get those two things
confused.
That's really an important point.
I think you're right, laypeople do get those two points confused.
And I do remember, we spoke a little bit about this in round one, and I spoke about what
I use as a continuum, and I call it the dispute resolution continuum.
And if you go all the way to the left-hand side of that continuum, you start off with
negotiation.
As I mentioned earlier, direct negotiation, you and I are either doing a deal or we have
a dispute.
And I'll say to you, look, Mark, we have a dispute over here.
I don't think it behooves either of us to try to take this to court if we can resolve
it to our satisfaction without that.
Let's at least sit down and talk about it and explore what some of your concerns and
needs are, share some of mine, and see if you might be able to come up with some resolution.
So that's negotiation.
As you move along from left to right, along that dispute resolution continuum, then come
to if negotiation fails, we can do mediation, as I said earlier.
Mediation rarely, to put it into very simple terms, is facilitated negotiation, where the
mediator is a specialist and an expert on the process of negotiation and effective communication.
And he facilitates that communication and negotiation between the parties in a way that
it remains productive and purposeful and helps the parties to reach resolution.
What's important to point out in mediation is the mediator has no decision-making power.
So the mediator can't say, this is what I'm ruling or this is what I'm saying you
have to do.
There is none of that at all.
The mediator has no decision-making power.
He is a process facilitator and he helps the parties reach agreement.
If parties do not reach agreement, or if one party doesn't want to agree, there's no agreement.
And that's all there is to it.
Having said that, statistics typically show that between 85% and 95% of cases settle.
Even litigator cases usually settle on the steps of the courthouse.
That's only about 5% of cases that actually reach trial.
What we're trying to do is to bring that forward.
Why spend hundreds of thousands of dollars on litigation, where we can just bring that
whole line forward and settle it now before it gets to that stage.
So that's what mediation is.
A mediation is quite broadly used in court districts across the U.S.
And I'm pleased for Canada from what I've read as well and across the world.
It's becoming quite a popular form of resolution, particularly given COVID now, where there's
so much backlog on the courthouse dockets.
Many judges will recommend or even order mediation before they're actually further in the process.
Not uncommon at all.
So that's mediation.
And I call that, well, that's called this facilitative mediation.
As we move further along the continuum, we get to what's called evaluative mediation.
It's also mediation, but it's closer to arbitration in the sense that usually the people who practice
facilitative mediation are usually lawyers that have been in litigation for many years
or retired judges who are always in the courtroom mindset.
And evaluative mediation typically is the mediator will put subtle pressure on the
parties using the law as leverage.
And they'll say, you know, they'll meet the party separately.
And I'll say, look, if you went to court in this, this is what I haven't done.
Many of these cases, this is probably the outcome you would get.
So I would urge you to settle on that basis because otherwise it may be a lot worse for
you and they go to the other party and do something similar.
And so they are trying to sort of subtly strong on the parties into agreement based
on their experience of litigation.
So it's not yet quite ordering them to do it, but it's very strong pressure that
they are asserting upon the parties to agree.
So that's evaluative mediation, much closer in the continuum to arbitration.
Moving further to the rights is arbitration and arbitration is distinct from
mediation in that mediation is a facilitative process based on negotiation
where arbitration is an adjudicative process where the arbitrator is basically
a judge for hire.
Usually he's an expert on the subject matter of the case.
For example, if it's a construction dispute, he will have had experience in
litigating constructed cases and be quite familiar with construction law.
He will hear the parties cases.
Sometimes it'll be discovery.
Sometimes it won't.
There may be evidence presented in the way of witnesses.
Maybe not.
I mean, they can design how they want that to be as opposed to a court case,
which is based on civil procedure.
So the nice thing about arbitration is you can decide and design how extensive
you want the formality of the arbitration to be.
But at the end of the day, you have no choice in arbitration.
The arbitrator is going to make the decision for you.
It's typically binding where before you go into that arbitration,
you sign an arbitration agreement, which binds you to anything the
arbitrator says.
So that's basically an adjudicated process like a court.
But the difference is it's less formal.
You can do it quicker.
You can design how formal you want the process to be, how much discovery you
want the process to involve and so on and so forth.
And that's the arbitration component of it.
Arbitration is very difficult to appeal.
It's almost impossible to appeal.
That's part of the arbitration process.
Only two cases in which you can appeal it.
And that is where it's clear that the arbitrator made a gross error in
terms of law or whether there's an unconscionable decision.
Both difficult things to prove.
And it's almost impossible, I would say, to appeal an arbitration.
And then finally, moving further to the right, you've got litigation.
And of course, litigation is, we all know litigation is all too well,
unfortunately.
And that's, of course, the most extreme.
So as you move from the left to the right,
the process has become more invasive and more expensive and costly.
As you go from negotiation and more adversarial.
So moving from that left to right continuum, as you're moving,
you get into more adversity and you get more expensive and costly.
And it takes more time.
At the end of the day, I think it's important for parties to decide,
knowing that continuum, which makes more sense.
Once you go straight to litigation, it's difficult to deescalate.
If you start on the left hand side of the continuum, you can always escalate.
So parties need to think about that very carefully and kind of remove
the emotional side of the dispute when they're trying to make a decision.
What process would be best to try to resolve this?
I find it interesting that so many people don't think about that continuum
and they default to litigation as the way that you would resolve a dispute.
I was chatting with an organization some time ago
and we were working on a case together and they defaulted straight to litigation.
I was like, guys, before you go down this road,
I really want you to consult some very good legal counsel
because going down this road is going to lead to a significant cost to outlay.
And it may not necessarily be worth it or worth your time
or worth the headaches or worth the press.
And unpredictable.
And very unpredictable.
You can try and forecast it as best you can, but you don't know for sure.
Unless you have a slam dunk case, even then it may not necessarily be worth it.
So I like your advice around starting off on the left hand side
and then escalating from there because you may be able to resolve it
before you get to a litigation procedure.
And what I will say for the listeners, just so that you know,
we're going to preface this and we're going to make sure
that we do it in the intro.
None of this is legal advice.
You should still seek the counsel of a qualified attorney at all times
with any kind of legal stuff that you're going into, obviously.
This is meant purely for informational purposes.
So please don't use this as legal advice.
Please go and seek the counsel of a qualified attorney
that can help you along the way.
That being said, let's get into the weeds.
When it comes to mediation, I find this to be very interesting
and facilitated negotiation, I should say maybe more broadly
because you get brought into situations where you may have two parties
that don't want to go to the litigation route.
They want to try and resolve it.
They recognize the cost or the expense or the unpredictable nature of litigation.
They want to try and resolve it before they get there.
And you get brought into situations where you are maybe a neutral third party
trying to facilitate a conversation between two other parties
who disagree on something that want to get something done as a mediator,
as someone who deals with this kind of stuff all the time.
What is the process that you think about when going into those kinds of situations
to try and make it as productive as possible?
I try to get my mindset to a place, Mark.
I understand that both parties, from the way they see things, make sense to them.
It may not make sense to me, it may not make sense to you,
but it makes sense to them based on their needs, based on their concerns,
based on their fears, based on how the filters through which they've processed
some of the information.
And I say this many times, where somebody will come to speak to me,
I'll hear the one side and I'll say, you know, it makes so much sense.
I can't see where the other side is coming from.
And then I'll speak to the other side and boom, there's some information
that suddenly opens it up and things that make sense from their side too.
And what typically happens in any kind of a dispute
or any kind of argument or debate that we might be engaged in,
I see things very dogmatically from my side
and you see things very dogmatically from your side.
I remain in my space and you remain in your space
and there's never any exchange for me to make sure
that I get a sense of how you're seeing it and vice versa.
So, and I think part of that emerges from the fact that people confuse
understanding with agreeing.
I think people think that if I really make an effort of understanding you
and I explain to you, I say, Mark, let me see,
make sure that I understand you 100% here.
And I then go on to argue your case more compellingly
than you can argue with yourself,
that people think, well, that means I must agree with you.
No, it doesn't. It means that I've understood you.
It doesn't mean that I've agreed with you.
And people have to in their own mind be able to separate understanding with agreeing.
So, what I try to sort of make that very much part of the media issue
and that I facilitate understanding, I make it very clear.
All I'm asking you to do is to try to understand,
putting yourself in the other part issues, how they see it.
Because if you're going to change their mind,
you have to know where their mind is at
and what it's like to be in their mind.
So, the first thing is really to understand how are they seeing it.
To the extent that you can actually bring yourself to the point,
that makes sense. If I was them, that makes a lot of sense to me.
I can see how they might be seeing it that way.
So, facilitating that understanding
and making sure that parties realize
they can understand perfectly well without necessarily agreeing.
I always like to refer the story of my mentor, Roger Fish in Harvard.
I think you went to that program in Harvard.
I did, I did, yeah.
Probably when you and Roger had already passed away,
Roger wrote the Getting to Yes book.
And he was a fascinating individual in many regards
and he was still very fortunate enough to still get his tutors.
But he used to argue cases in front of the Supreme Court
and the way he would argue his cases was
he would start off by arguing his opponent's case.
And he would argue it more eloquently and more articulately
than his opponent argued it himself.
And the judge would become confused
and the judge would say, Mr. Fisher, whose side are you on?
And Roger would say, you know,
bear with me your honor, I'm getting there.
And after having a demonstrated immaculate understanding
of the other side, he would then say,
and your honor, there is a different way
of looking at this as well.
And then start presenting his case,
a very compelling debating technique.
And I think in negotiation, that's also equally important
where I spend much more time really trying to understand you
and then trying to assert my own demands.
Hey, listeners, I wanna tell you about another company
that I run called Content Callout.
It is a thought leadership brand marketing company.
Now, what does that mean?
It means that we take you as an executive or entrepreneur,
a leader of a small or medium sized business
and we turn you into a thought leader online.
We take your personal brand and we amp it up to 11
so that you can lead with confidence
knowing that people will recognize you,
recognize your brand and recognize your business
because of the thought leadership approach
that you've taken on social media
through content creation and content distribution
as well as engaging with all of your following online.
How do you get involved in this?
Easy, easy, easy.
Just go to contentcallout.com forward slash get started
and you will see there three different options
that will allow you to take your thought leadership brand
for yourself and for your business to the next level.
We are super excited to talk to you about this.
We've seen some massive growth with the businesses
that we've been working with.
Very, very exciting time for us.
Look at that, we appreciate it.
Now back to your show.
Something that you said piqued my interest there
and I think we've all been guilty of this.
You said something to the effect of people being dogmatic
about what they believe in.
And sometimes I find that when people are negotiating
there's almost like a religious adherence
to the position that they have.
Is there a way that you help them to,
I don't want to say overcome that adherence
to their position because that's important
but maybe to try and understand more of the interests
of the other parties,
how do you take them through that process?
Well, yes, what you really want to do is they come in,
they could exchange the word dogmatic for rigid
and I think they're both true.
I think they're dogmatic about the position
but they're also very rigid about the positions.
They'd really dug in to think about a big oak tree
with its roots firmly planted into the ground.
That's kind of where the position is at when they come in.
So you need to be able to loosen the earth
around the positions and to make it much less rigid
in terms of being able to then allow them
to think a little bit more broadly.
And as you know, one of the keystones
of interest-based negotiation,
which we're both very familiar with,
and I feel almost inadequate in presenting this
because it's so, I mean, any negotiation material
you look at today speaks about interests.
Not everybody has a depth of understanding of it
but it's become overused and it's become,
everybody's rebranding it in some way or another.
And I think we spoke about it last time
in terms of the fact there's a lot more
in negotiation, technique and skill and processes
and interests and positions.
But in terms of the loosening the earth
around those positions,
it's important to work through the party's position
in trying to get below the position
because a position really is a solution.
So for example, if I say to you,
we want $100,000 for that.
Well, that's one solution.
But what are you really looking for?
You're looking for fair compensation.
And the other way is you can provide fair compensation
and just $100,000, okay?
I may be able to offer you work in the future.
We're doing another project in place X, Y or Z.
We do have an opening there.
Is that something that might interest you
as part of the compensation package?
But as long as we stuck on $100,000, which is a position,
that's one possible solution.
That's not the only solution.
And so a position, when they present a position,
they're usually presenting the solution.
We have to understand what the problem is
to which they're presenting the solution.
So in that example that I gave you,
the solution is $100,000.
But the problem really is
how do we reach fair compensation?
And I will reframe it.
I will use the reframing technique a lot.
And I'll say, so what you really look,
when they come in and say $100,000,
I'm not going to use my active listening
to reinforce the position.
I'll never use active listening
to reinforce something that's not useful.
So I will use my active listening
to reframe that into something more useful,
a less rigid position,
and something that helps us define the problem.
And I say, so what you're really looking for over here
is fair compensation.
Is that correct?
I've understood you correctly.
Yes, absolutely.
Well, fair compensation, we just, what have we just done?
We just loosened the earth
around those deep roots of the big oak tree
of what you demand, $100,000.
And now it becomes fair compensation.
In the process, what you've done
is you've also created so many alternatives, right?
To what may solve the ultimate problem,
which is fair compensation.
And that's where we want to go to.
We just put in a complex negotiation right now.
And always they try to get you,
well, make us an offer, make us an offer.
And you don't want to do that
because whatever offer you make,
you're going to be negotiating against yourself
because they're going to flinch
and they got to, well, you got to do better than that.
So the technique that we use talking about options
is we never present one offer.
We'll present multiple equivalent simultaneous offers.
We could do option A
and sort of a list of components option A,
option B, a list of components option B and option C.
It makes it a lot more difficult for them to flinch
because then they start looking unreasonable,
but nothing in these offers appeal to you.
I love that approach.
One of the key things that I think a lot of people think
about when it comes to mediation
is the frustration and tension that may pop up
in these sort of long protracted discussions.
And I would imagine,
and you can correct me if I'm wrong,
that it's very rare to come to a solution in one meeting.
I would imagine that there's several discussions
that need to be had by both parties.
How do you manage the tension that may exist?
Or do you manage it?
Is there a way for you to leverage that
in the conversations throughout these long discussions
that you have between both parties?
Well, you've got to look at mediation or negotiation
for that matter is an evolutionary process.
And typically when they come into the mediation
in the morning, there's a lot of tension.
It is anger almost, you know, there's emotions
that one side doesn't want to look at the other side
as it progresses and as communication takes place.
And as understanding occurs, as I mentioned earlier,
that starts diminishing and decreasing.
You can't do that instantly.
That's got to evolve during the day.
So of course, you're managing that all the time.
And what you want to be careful of is that
it doesn't obstruct the productive negotiation.
Now, if there are strong emotions over there,
you can't tell them,
don't get so emotional or calm down.
That doesn't work.
So you've got to allow them to vent a little.
I think in the history of mankind,
telling someone to calm down has never caused them
to calm down.
It doesn't work.
Now, people still do it despite the fact
that it's been ultimately proven
that it never, ever works.
Yes.
I'm sure Adam said to Eve, calm down.
And that was probably the beginning of his problem.
So managing that tension and managing that frustration
as an evolutionary process takes time.
And do you preface?
And time and skill and process.
Yes.
Do you preface the conversation with both parties to say,
hey, as we go into this,
there are going to be some situations
where you may get frustrated
or the other party may get frustrated.
You may get tense.
The other party may get tense.
If and when that happens,
do you have like rules that you said at the beginning?
Like if you want to call a timeout,
you call a timeout.
How do you preface that conversation?
So many mediators,
and sometimes I will do that.
It depends on the situation.
And many mediators will start the process
of what they call ground rules.
You've got to be careful with those ground rules
because the last thing you want to do
is to come over as an authoritative school master
telling them how to behave.
So that becomes part of the negotiations.
And I call that,
and I'm sure you've heard this term,
the talks about the talks.
So we may have some discussion,
maybe even in pre-mediation conversations
we have over the phone and so on.
And I'll always have some pre-mediation conversations
with attorneys at a minimum.
And we'll want to have the talks before the talks.
Are there any things at all
that concern you in terms of how this process might go?
And the racings.
Well, we're concerned about in joint sessions
when we've tried to talk,
just got so emotional and so angry,
we just got so angry at each other
and just erupted into a swearing match
and it's been unproductive.
I'll say, okay, how can I help you manage that
in a way that it won't derail negotiation?
What ideas might you have?
So I'm getting their input.
So they'll be negotiating the process is what we're doing.
And again, that's something I've gotten
from international negotiations as well.
I mean, big international negotiations,
a lot of work is put into the talks about the talks
and setting that all up.
So I've borrowed that from international negotiations
and use that on a much smaller scale
in terms of the mediations and negotiates
that we do every day.
It strikes me that the need for diplomacy
and those types of conversations is so important
because you can't come barreling in with your own ideas
about how things should run.
I love that you start the conversation with asking them
about what they foresee as what my challenges occur.
That in and of itself is such good advice
for the listeners.
I hope you caught that.
The whole idea is prior to going into the negotiation itself,
you would start what Raphael calls the talks
about the talks, which is basically pre-negotiations
to say, hey, what do you see as things that may stall this?
Where do you think you might get frustrated?
What do you see as challenges
that we may need to overcome?
Where have things gone wrong in the past?
Those kinds of sort of broad questions
to generate discussion around how you could help them.
That is such a key piece of advice.
And I think that so many people going into complex
negotiations, and I would say that your approach
is really good for complex negotiation,
going into complex negotiations,
miss that out because they're so used to the tactical
that comes into it, right?
They think it's about a price as per your example
or an amount when it may be much deeper rooted than that
and you have to get to the emotion of it
more than anything else.
Yeah, and it's also important for management as well
because management are involved in negotiations
without even realizing it.
Yes.
So for example, if I come to one of my employees
and I said, please have this report done by tomorrow,
and they said, I'm terribly sorry, sir,
so that can't turn that around by tomorrow.
So one way is to, through authority and command,
well, I command you and demand that you do it
by tomorrow, otherwise you fire.
And that's not gonna get me very far.
But if I say to them, I say, you're not getting
to those infos loosening the earth
around those roots, that rigid position.
And I say, can you explain to me some of the constraints
you might have, because if I understand that,
we may be able to find some solution to that.
And then they'll say, well, I've got to do this form,
this person, I've got to do that for that person.
And I'll say, do you have any ideas
of how I might shift that around?
What are the priorities?
So you're asking them for the solution.
I'm using similar techniques and management.
You know, there's all sorts of theory
about good management and so on,
but managers, what they don't realize really
is that there's so much involved
that relates to negotiation and mediation.
Big time.
I can imagine that at some point in the mediation process,
you've got to start closing towards a final solution.
But sometimes corralling both parties
to keep their agreements is probably quite challenging.
Is there a way that you can get people to commit
and keep to their commitments
on what has been agreed to throughout
so that you can get to a close?
How do you manage that?
So that gets to your earlier question, Mark,
which I think I don't fully address,
and that is you ask about getting the mediation resolved
in the meeting or not.
So, you know, some mediations will get resolved
in a meeting, and what we will typically do
is make sure that we write some kind of agreement
and get that agreement signed in the meeting,
even if it's on the back of a napkin.
But we will get something signed
if agreement is reached.
But many times what happens is,
at the end of the mediation,
I realize there is room here for agreement.
We haven't gotten to complete agreement just yet,
but there is room for agreement.
There's definitely room to move over here,
and I think I can do something.
I will continue working with the parties offline
and working towards agreement there,
and again, it will always,
and then we've got an email track
and I'll always summarize in the emails
as we're sort of building up towards agreement.
But at the end of the day,
when we have reached agreement,
you know, I will always make sure
to have something signed.
Now, one mistake that I've made in the past,
and I don't make it anymore,
is that what has happened in the past
is the attorneys say,
well, yes, thank you,
I think we've got it from here,
and I think they've got it from there.
But they haven't.
It falls apart.
So I never leave it to the attorneys
until we've got something signed.
So when they say to me,
yes, you know, we think we've got it from here,
no, they haven't got it from there.
They make a mess of it,
nine times out of 10.
So I need to stay involved
until we've got something signed.
You ever had a situation
where someone has used the mediation process
to escalate the situation
and purposefully evade solution
to try and drive it towards
more of the right-hand side of the spectrum
to get to litigation?
The only time that happens
is in coded mediation.
So, for example, in many districts,
and I'm sure it's in Canada as well,
particularly in family law,
probably more common in family law
than anything else,
is where the judge will order mediation.
And not only that,
it's oftentimes ordered within the court system
whereby they've got mediators
that are not terribly well trained or qualified,
and they'll spend two or three hours
with the parties to try to mediate a solution.
But even if it's not,
if they come because the judge has ordered it,
sometimes it's a danger
that a pro forma to move beyond to litigation.
So you've got to be a little careful of that.
And if that is the case,
if it's a court ordered mediation,
you suspect that's what it is,
you're better off spending time
in that mediation,
educating the parties
about what it looks like
moving towards the right
and what the options are of resolution
rather than trying to go straight
into the mediation process.
I'm going to paint a picture for you
and I'd like to see how you would respond.
Now, this is a specific example,
and you could tell me
that this doesn't necessarily make sense
if it doesn't make sense for you.
Let's say, for example,
you get to a point
where the only option
is to go to litigation.
Both parties are fighting.
You can't find a way for people
to agree with each other.
You've gone from negotiation to mediation,
maybe even explored arbitration,
but they've just decided,
screw it, we're going to go straight to litigation.
Do you have like a Hail Mary
that you throw at the end
to try and stop that from happening?
Or do you just say,
all right, I've done what I have to do.
And you know,
what's the way that you sleep well at night
knowing that you've done
everything that you can do
before they try and destroy each other in court?
Well, two responses to that.
The first response is that
in order to resolve a dispute,
it has to be ripe for resolution,
as I call it.
And sometimes it's not ripe for resolution.
It's again, like international affairs,
where sometimes there have to be
a few shots fired across the border
until both parties realize
what we're getting ourselves into.
That's the one aspect.
You've got to ask yourself,
is this dispute actually ripe for resolution?
And it may not be.
They may have to go through
some volleys of litigation
before it actually becomes ripe for resolution.
The second point I want to make
is when a person says,
I want to litigate this,
in using our negotiation jargon, if you will,
essentially that's a position.
That's again, a rigid position.
I'm going to litigate.
And we can treat that as a position
and try to find the interests.
Why would you litigate?
For what purpose would you litigate?
And what would be your underlying interest
in litigating as opposed to finding some
cheaper and more effective means of resolution?
And sort of walking them down that path
of trying to understand what those interests
and trying to loosen, again,
those deep roots of that big oak tree.
Yeah.
But again, never imposing, never say,
if they decide that's what it is,
you've got to be able to walk away.
Try to help them to sort of see what that looks like
and try to understand what some of the interests are,
try to find other solutions.
And you might say,
well, I'm just afraid that I'll agree
to something I might regret.
So at that point I'll say,
but how about we try to mediate
and look at some various options
without any commitment?
Then I'll try to find solutions to the interests
as opposed to responding to the position.
This is my interpretation.
I find the mediation process to be
a lot more collaborative than the litigation process,
at least on the surface from an outsider
I was chatting with a litigator once
who was the chief litigator of a firm,
which I won't name,
but that person was seen as like the chief attack dog
of that organization.
And their job was solely to seek and destroy
and like go in and destroy
as much as humanly possible of the other party.
It wasn't collaborative.
There was no sort of way to find common interests.
It was attack, attack all the time.
And that person was built for that role, right?
And there are certain litigators
that are just designed purely for that role.
And we need those people.
I'm not saying that we don't need those people,
but it seemed like such a acidic process
and such a vindictive process
that on the surface it was just like,
whoa, this is crazy.
This guy, all he thought about was attack.
It didn't seem collaborative whatsoever.
Am I wrong there?
No, you're absolutely right.
And as you mentioned correctly,
sometimes we need that.
The problem is in corporations
where they have in-house counsel,
that's all they have.
And the way I look at it is
you need both the Department of Defense,
which is what that is,
and you need a Department of State,
which deals with the diplomacy side
and they need to balance one another out.
The problem is in many situations,
such as that corporation
and many corporations like that
have the Department of Defense,
but they don't have the Department of State.
And I think corporation would be well served
to have both those departments,
in-house legal teams,
both the Department of Defense
and the Department of State
and use them as necessary.
Imagine the United States,
well, it's hard to imagine the United States anyway.
Imagine the United States
to the Department of Defense only
and no Department of State.
Yeah, and no diplomacy.
Yes.
Yeah, interesting.
I like the way that you tie that to,
essentially it would be like a large organization
is much like a government,
to a large extent.
It is.
And having those departments are key,
whether or not they're individual people
is another thing in town.
Right, right, right.
In fact, a large corporation being well advised
to actually have a completely separate Department of State
with a VP of negotiation
and dispute resolution and so on.
I've seen a lot of chatter about this recently
where people are arguing for sort of like
the chief negotiation officer role
within an organization to keep that diplomacy going.
Correct.
I think that's something we may be worth looking at
for larger corporations.
Yeah, very interesting.
Well, as always, my friend,
this has been a fascinating discussion.
I sincerely appreciate you coming on,
but I'm sure that there are gonna be a lot of people
that wanna follow you and follow your stuff online.
How do they do that?
Okay, well, so my website is,
my name is LapenNegotiationServices.com.
So that's easy enough.
I've just recently, very proudly,
just started a YouTube channel.
Oh, good.
And that's under my regular name,
Rafael Lapen, R-A-P-H-A-E-L
and last name L-A-P as in Peter, I and as in Nancy.
So I would love for people to subscribe to that.
We're gonna be putting out some videos,
stuff a few videos up there already.
And again, always, I try to make sure
that this information that's relevant
and practical for people to use.
You know, that certainly is good.
And people should feel free.
I'm always available for reaching out
and I love hearing from people.
So I would love to connect with anybody
who would just see for to connect with me.
Awesome.
For the listeners, just so that you know,
we will link out to the YouTube channel.
We will also link out to Rafael's website
as well as his social profiles in our show notes.
Just go to the website for that
and look at this episode.
Rafael, thank you so much for being here
and thank you so much for sharing your wisdom.
Certainly.
Certainly, Mark.
Hey friends, thanks so much for listening to this episode.
If you enjoyed it,
please share it with friends and colleagues
so that they can benefit from it as well.
If you find Negotiations Ninja podcast worthy,
please go onto iTunes
and give us a cool rating with a nice review.
We certainly appreciate every single one that we get
because it helps us to understand who is listening,
how they're listening and what it is they like.
If there's something that you would like me to discuss
around negotiation, influence, or persuasion,
give me a shout.
You know how to reach me on social media
or you can get me on my website,
which is www.negotiations.ninja.